Frank L. Engel

Geographer





Geographer and researcher with 10+ years of experience developing new tools, technology, and apps using remote sensing to solve real-world problems. Very familiar with standard software design practices, operational deployment of technology and hardware, and providing practical training. Passionate about good project management and clear communication through scientific publications, documentation, and other media.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

U.S. Geological Survey - Hydrologic Remote Sensing Branch

(Jan 2022 - Present)

Geographer | 40 hours/week | GS 13

- Project Manager of the National Imagery Management System (NIMS), a cloud infrastructure supporting ingesting over 20,000 images daily from hundreds of cameras at USGS gaging locations nationwide.
- Developed non-contact streamflow methods and software using image velocimetry.
- Recognized Subject Matter Expert in using and deploying cameras for image velocimetry gaging techniques.

Key Achievement: Developed and advocated for national adoption of non-contact streamflow methods, policies, procedures, and training resulting in 100s of new velocity gages and discrete measurements.

U.S. Geological Survey – Oklahoma-Texas Water Science Center

(Jun 2017 – Dec 2021)

Geographer | 40 hours/week | GS 12

- Developed CameraDCP to automate the collection of scientific imagery with single-board computers.
- Developed flood inundation models for the Texas Hill Country.
- Designed & conducted novel hydraulic studies with hydroacoustics to monitor near-shore sediment transport and beach replenishment.

Key Achievement: Helped find significant efficiency in NWIS Imagery project, which led to a reduction in costs to Program of 23%.

U.S. Geological Survey - Illinois Water Science Center

(Jun 2015 - Jun 2017)

Geographer | 40 hours/week | GS 12

- Evaluated new hydroacoustic sensors and technology through the former Office of Surface Water.
- Recognized Subject Matter Expert on hydroacoustics in novel or atypical deployments.

Key Achievement: Published two high-impact multi-agency scientific studies detailing the potential impacts of barge traffic on Asian Carp front progression.

U.S. Geological Survey – Illinois Water Science Center

(Mar 2014 - Jun 2015)

Geographer | 40 hours/week | GS 11

- Co-developed Velocity Mapping Toolbox software; a recognized standard application for use with hydroacoustics.
- Conducted several national training classes on the proper use of hydroacoustics.
- Secured new projects by working with local and national cooperators.

U.S. Geological Survey - Illinois Water Science Center

(Apr 2013 - Mar 2014)

Geographer | 40 hours/week | GS 7

- Formalized code used in Velocity Mapping Toolbox, enabling software look & feel standardization.
- Completed fieldwork and scientific analysis for several projects as assigned.

U.S. Geological Survey - Illinois Water Science Center

(Apr 2012 - Apr 2013)

Hydrologist-Student Trainee | 20-30 hours/week | GS 5

• Completed fieldwork and scientific analysis for several projects as assigned.

EDUCATION

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

PhD in Geography (Civil & Env Eng Minor)

(Sep 2007 - May 2014)

Texas State University-San Marcos

MS in Geography

3.88 GPA

3.92 GPA

(Sep 2005 - Dec 2007)

Texas State University-San Marcos

BS in Physical Geography (Music Minor)

3.34 GPA

(Sep 1999 - May 2005)

SELECT PUBLICATIONS DEMONSTRATING KEY EXPERTISE

Fulton, J.W., Engel, F.L., Eggleston, J.R., Best, H.R., Nicotra, M.J., Gyves, M.C., and Kunkle, G.A., in review, Measuring river discharge using Doppler velocity radars: U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods Report.

Legleiter, C.J., Kinzel, P.J., Engel, F.L., Harrison, L.R., and Hewitt, G. 2024. A two-dimensional, reach-scale implementation of Space Time Image Velocimetry (STIV) and comparison to Particle Image Velocimetry (PIV). Earth Surface Processes and Landforms. https://doi.org/10.1002/esp.5878.

Duan, J.G., Engel, F.L., and Cadogan, A., 2023, Discharge estimation using video recordings from small unoccupied aircraft systems. Journal of Hydraulic Engineering, 149 (11), https://doi.org/10.1061/JHEND8.HYENG-13591.

Engel, F.L., Jackson, P.R., and Murphy, E.A., 2018, Flow hydraulics and mixing characteristics in and downstream of Brandon Road Lock, Joliet, Illinois: U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report. https://doi.org/10.3133/sir20185094.

Davis, J.J., Jackson, P.R., Engel, F.L., LeRoy, J.Z., Neeley, R.N., Finney, S.T., Murphy, E.A., 2016, Entrainment, retention, and transport of freely swimming fish in junction gaps between commercial barges operating on the Illinois Waterway, Journal of Great Lakes Research. 42(4), 837-848, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jglr.2016.05.005.

SKILLS

Unoccupied Aerial Systems Remote Sensing Project Management Image Velocimetry Computer Vision Hydraulics and Turbulence Geographic Information Systems Hydroacoustics **AGILE Product Owner** Sediment Transport Geomorphology **Uncertainty Analysis**

REFERENCES

Jack Eggleston Hydrologic Remote Sensing Branch, Chief +1 434-962-0972 jegglest@usgs.gov

Daniel Pearson **NWIS Modernization Program Coordinator** +1 512-517-6545 dpearson@usgs.gov

Molly Wood Hydrologic Networks Branch, Chief +1 208-850-9929 mswood@usgs.gov

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

python **** matlab bash/linux iavascript

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Gitlab (USGS) @fengel

GitHub @frank-engel-usgs

A Hobbies gravelbiking, camping, reading